Guide to the James T. Sears Papers, 1918-2011 and undated, bulk 1950-2004 RL.01162
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Jack Nichols Papers, 1940-2005 and undated, 34 boxes
  - Nichols Correspondence, 1952-2005 and undated, 10 boxes
    - Publisher correspondence, 1988-2004, 6-10 of 10 folders (Box 264)
    - Sears, James T., 1998-2005 (Box 264)
    - Skir, Leo, 1982-1995 (Box 264)
    - Tomcat Chronicles correspondence, 1993, 2003 (Box 264)
    - TV contracts and related material, 1994-2003, 2 folders (Box 264)
    - Writing and business correspondence, 1969-2005, 1 of 13 folders (Box 264)
    - Writing and business correspondence, 1969-2005, 2-13 of 13 folders (Box 265)
  - Nichols Personal Files, 1940-2004 and undated, bulk 1969-2000, 1 box
    Includes files and ephemera from Nichols' childhood through late in his life. Diplomas, grades, and a certificate of baptism document elements of his early life. Course evaluations from a philosophy class in which his book Men's Liberation was assigned reflect some of the reactions the public had to Nichols' work. Press material and clippings as well as book publishing contracts document the some of the business aspects of his professional life. Personal, medical, and financial papers complete the series. Organized alphabetically.
    [Some items removed to Oversize Material. Contents of diskette migrated to server; please contact Research Services for assistance in accessing this material.]
    - Badpuppy commemorative coin, undated (Box 266)
    - Biographical press material, 2001 (Box 266)
    - Correspondence notes, 1988-1989, undated (Box 266)
    - Course evaluations, 1976 (Box 266)
    - Cruise information; Clarke family material, 1976, undated (Box 266)
    - Diary entries[?], undated (Box 266)
    - Dinner for Nichols, undated (Box 266)
    - Diplomas and grades, 1954-1971 (Box 266)
    - Legal, financial, and employment papers, 1966-1980 (Box 266)
    - Medical and personal papers, 1995-1996 (Box 266)
    - Notes, photographs, and clippings, 1973-1987, undated (Box 266)
    - Personal clippings and printed material, 1940-1970, undated (Box 266)
    - Personal and writing files, 1964-2004, undated, 2 folders (Box 266)
    - Photographic material, undated (Box 266)
    - Post, photograph, and memorial cards, 1993, undated (Box 266)
    - Publishing contracts, 1971-2003 (Box 266)
    - Various personal papers, 1972-1990 (Box 266)
    - Warren Adkins check copy, 1967 May 6 (Box 266)
  - Nichols Serials, 1969-2004, 4 boxes
    Consists of partial runs of serial publications. While most publications focus on gay issues, several serials address alternative spirituality, notably a mostly complete run of the central Florida-based Paradox. Issues of serials in which Nichols published work, particularly Contax and Et Cetera, are also housed in this series. Some original copies of newspaper publications, including issues of Gay, Gay News, The Gayzette, and Screw, can be found in Oversize Material. Organized alphabetically by title.
    - Companion (Box 266)
    - Contax-Intimate Horoscope (Box 267)
    - Man on the Moon-Paradox (Box 268)
    - Paradox-Where It's At (Box 269)
  - Nichols Subject Files, 1972-2004 and undated, 2 boxes
    Contains files kept by Nichols on a variety of topics, chiefly social issues. Folders of material related to close friend and lover Lige Clarke make up the largest grouping. These include some of Clarke's early school and personal papers as well as correspondence and information related to his violent death during a robbery in Mexico. Documentation of the lives and early deaths of activists Foster Gunnison and David Combs are included along with a file on the suspicious death of New York transvestite Marsha P. Johnson. Nichols' interest in anarchist philosophy and action is documented in the Anarchism grouping, and some information about the New Age group Renewal is housed in this subseries as well. Research material related to writings on Logan Carter and men's liberation complete the series. Organized alphabetically by subject.
    [Some items removed to Oversize Material. Contents of CD migrated to server; please contact Research Services for assistance in accessing this material.]
    - Anarchism, 1986-1994 (Box 269)
    - Carter, Logan, 1987 (Box 269)
    - Clarke, Lige, family, and related, 1972-2004, undated, 1-2 of 6 folders (Box 269)
    - Clarke, Lige, family, and related, 1972-2004, undated, 3-6 of 6 folders (Box 270)
    - Cure AIDS Now, 1986-1994, undated (Box 270)
    - Gittings, Barbara/Lahusen, Kay, 2001, undated (Box 270)
    - Gunnison, Foster memorial, 1994 Jan.-Sept. (Box 270)
    - Johnson, Marsha P. [Malcolm Michaels] death, undated (Box 270)
    - Men's liberation research material, 1972-1974, 1 of 2 folders (Box 270)
    - Men's liberation research material, 1972-1974, 2 of 2 folders (Box 270)
    - New Options/Renewal, 1982-1983 (Box 270)
    - Wicker, Randy/Combs, David, 1973-1995 (Box 270)
  - Nichols Writings, 1959-2004 and undated, 14 boxes
    Divided into subseries housing Articles, Book Manuscripts, and Writings by Others. The Articles Subseries primarily consists of published articles written by Nichols, notably the Homosexual Citizen (written with Lige Clarke) and Homosexual Anarchist columns written for Screw. Copies of the serial works The Calamus Chronicles (originally The Tomcat Chronicles, which became the basis for his 2004 book The Tomcat Chronicles) and the fictional Drop the Soap are in this subseries; numerous articles written for print and online publications, among them Gay Today and the mainstream Florida Today are included as well. Various articles, poems, and diary entries, some unpublished, make up the rest of the subseries. The Book Manuscript Subseries consists of various drafts of major works by Nichols. His memoir of his life and work with Lige Clarke, first drafted after Clarke's death in 1975 (and variously called Elijah and The Best Thing That Ever Happened to Me) are housed in this subseries, as are many iterations of his unpublished autobiography (at different times titled Evolution of a Friend, With the Love of Comrades, and The Guardian Dragon of Hoo Hoo Park). Other works found in this subseries are his unpublished work on transvestite and transexual identity Sissies and his published works I Have More Fun With You Than Anybody (with Lige Clarke), The Gay Agenda, The Tomcat Chronicles, and sections of Welcome to Fire Island. Drafts of Nichols' anthology works The Lavender Manifesto and Onan, Onan Uber Alles complete the writings subseries. The Writings by Others Subseries contains drafts of works sent to Nichols, particularly sections of Tiger, Tiger by Louis Campbell (published as Jack Nichols, Gay Pioneer). Works by Vern Bullough, James T. Sears, and Leo Skir are also housed in this series. Organized alphabetically by predominant title.
    - Nichols Articles, 1959-2004 and undated
      - About Lige, 1975 (Box 270)
      - Acid trip account, 1967 May (Box 270)
      - Articles and Speeches, 1963-1996, undated, 1 of 3 folders (Box 270)
      - Articles and Speeches, 1963-1996, undated, 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 271)
      - Autobiographical notes, circa 1985 (Box 271)
      - Diary, essays, and poems, 1985, 1993, undated (Box 271)
      - Don't Fuck With Me Fellas, undated (Box 271)
      - Drop the Soap, various drafts, 1981-1988, undated, 4 folders (Box 271)
      - Duberman critique draft; gay-bashing articles, undated (Box 271)
      - A Few Kisses Ago; Homosexual Anarchist; Amerika, Amerika, undated (Box 271)
      - Florida Today column, 1988 Jan. 16 (Box 271)
      - Gay Today articles and notes, 1997-2004, undated, 5 folders (Box 271)
      - The Genius of Logan Carter, undated (Box 271)
      - German Students Reject Gay Militancy, undated (Box 271)
      - Homosexual Anarchist, 1987-1995, undated, 7 folders (Box 272)
      - The Homosexual Citizen articles, 1963-1973, undated, 5 folders (Box 272)
      - Letter drafts, 1982-1993 (Box 272)
      - Letters to editors, 1984-1996, 3 folders (Box 272)
      - Lige article - Outcome, 1990, 1998 (Box 272)
      - Men's liberation speech and originals for xerox, 1976-1990, undated (Box 272)
      - Men's lib writing--reviews/essays, 1976-1983 (Box 272)
      - Poems, 1990-1996, undated, 3 folders (Box 273)
      - Rememberances of My Religious and Philosophical Development During Adolescence, 1989 (Box 273)
      - Resumé, [1995] (Box 273)
      - The Tomcat/Calamus Chronicles, 1991 Apr.-1993 May, 6 folders (Box 273)
      - TWN [The Weekly News] articles, 1985-2004 (Box 273)
      - Screw columns, 1987-1995 (Box 273)
      - Untitled essay and poems, undated, 2 folders (Box 273)
      - Various articles and writings, 1959-2004, undated, 1-3 of 15 folders (Box 273)
      - Various articles and writings, 1959-2004, undated, 4-13 of 15 folders (Box 274)
      - Various articles and writings, 1959-2004, undated, 14-15 of 15 folders (Box 275)
      - We Were Talking About You, Walt Whitman, undated (Box 275)
      - Whitman and various articles, undated (Box 275)
    - Nichols Book Manuscripts, 1972-2000 and undated
      - Drop the Soap, various drafts, 1988, 1993, undated (Box 275)
      - Elijah, various drafts, undated, 1-3 of 22 folders (Box 275)
      - Elijah, various drafts, undated, 4-16 of 22 folders (Box 276)
      - Elijah, various drafts, undated, 17-22 of 22 folders (Box 277)
      - Evolution of a Friend, various drafts, 1995, undated, 1-5 of 29 folders (Box 277)
      - Evolution of a Friend, various drafts, 1995, undated, 6-14 of 29 folders (Box 278)
      - Evolution of a Friend, various drafts, 1995, undated, 15-25 of 29 folders (Box 279)
      - Evolution of a Friend, various drafts, 1995, undated, 26-29 of 29 folders (Box 280)
      - The Gay Agenda, various drafts, 1996, 1998, undated, 5 folders (Box 280)
      - I Have More Fun With You Than Anybody, copy and reviews, circa 1972, undated, 2 folders (Box 280)
      - The Lavender Manifesto, undated, 1-3 of 5 folders (Box 280)
      - The Lavender Manifesto, undated, 4-5 folders (Box 281)
      - Onan, Onan Uber Alles, undated, 2 folders (Box 281)
      - Sissies, 1978-1980, undated, 5 folders (Box 281)
      - The Tomcat Chronicles, 2000, undated, 9 folders (Box 282)
      - Untitled draft sections, undated, 1 of 2 folders (Box 282)
      - Untitled draft sections, undated, 2 of 2 folders (Box 283)
      - Welcome to Fire Island and unknown work excerpts, undated (Box 283)
    - Nichols Writings By Others, 1988-2004 and undated
      - Ayyar, Lige Clarke: Body and Soul, 2002 Dec. 2 (Box 283)
      - Bullough, Before Stonewall, circa 2001 (Box 283)
      - Cain, Jack Nichols Interview, circa 2000 (Box 283)
      - Cain, Wicker Interview Transcript, 1994 Sept. 2 (Box 283)
      - Campbell, Tiger, Tiger, various drafts, 2003-2004, undated, 5 folders (Box 283)
      - Clarke, Courier Journal letter to editor, undated (Box 283)
      - Sears, Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones, chapter 15, 1999 Aug. 5 (Box 283)
      - Skir, As Good As It Gets review, 1998 Jan. 8 (Box 283)
      - Skir, It's Only Me, 1989 (Box 283)
      - Skir, various writings, 1992-1993 (Box 283)
      - [Teal], A Peak in Darrien (screenplay) disks 023-026, 2000 (Box 283)
      - Unknown author [M.S.], Interview with Randy Wicker, 1988 (Box 283)
  - Nichols Oversize Material, 1969-2004 and undated, 4 boxes
    Comprises large items separated from subseries in the Jack Nichols Papers Series. Chiefly consists of newspaper and magazine clippings pertaining to Nichols' writings and personal interests. Topics include reviews of Nichols' writing, definitions of masculinity, perceptions of the gay community (especially related to gay-bashing or the AIDS epidemic), and politics. Some serial publications, including issues of Gay, Gay News, The Sentinel, and Screw can be found in Oversize Material. In addition, most originals of Nichols' regular columns for Screw, The Homosexual Citizen (with Lige Clarke) and Homosexual Anarchist are included. Organized alphabetically by series.
    - Oversize Nichols Clippings and Printed Material
      - Clippings from The Advocate and Gay, 1971-1976, undated (Box 284, Folder 1)
      - Newspaper article and review clippings, 1969-1996 (Box 284, Folder 2)
      - Men's liberation newspaper clippings, 1974-1994 (Box 284, Folder 3)
      - Review article clippings, 1975-2001 (Box 284, Folder 4)
      - Newspaper sections and clippings, 1975-2004 (Box 284, Folder 5)
    - Oversize Nichols Correspondence
      - Newspaper clippings, 1972-1998 (Box 284, Folder 6)
      - Newspaper clippings from friends, family, and business correspondence files, 1977-1986 (Box 284, Folder 7)
    - Oversize Nichols Personal Files
      - Newspaper clippings and cruise information, 1964-1994, undated (Box 284, Folder 8)
    - Oversize Nichols Serials
      - The Advocate and Baltimore Alternative, 1982, 1996 (Box 285, Folder 8)
      - Gay, 1969-1973 (Box 285, Folder 9)
      - The Gay News and Gayzette, 1975, 1980 (Box 285, Folder 10)
      - Screw, 1968-1995 (Box 285, Folder 11)
      - The Sentinel, 1981 (Box 286, Folder 12)
      - TWN [The Weekly News], 1988-1995 (Box 284, Folder 13)
      - Watermark, 1995-1996 (Box 284, Folder 14)
    - Oversize Nichols Subject Files
      - Newspaper clippings from files on anarchism, Logan Carter, Cure AIDS Now, and Lige Clarke, 1972-1994 (Box 284, Folder 15)
      - Newspaper and magazine clippings from files on Barbara Gittings and Kay Lahusen, men's liberation, and Randy Wicker and David Combs, 1972-2001 (Box 284, Folder 16)
    - Oversize Nichols Writings
      - Homosexual Anarchist originals, 1996-1998 (Box 287, Folder 17)
      - Homosexual Citizen originals, 1969-1972, 4 folders (Box 287, Folder 18-21)
      - Homosexual Citizen and Homosexual Anarchist originals, other clippings from Screw, 2 folders (Box 287, Folder 22-23)
      - Newspaper and magazine issues and clippings related to men's liberation and other topics, 1976-1996 (Box 286, Folder 24)
      - Newspaper clippings related to articles written by Nichols, 1970-2004 (Box 286, Folder 25)
      - Newspaper clippings related to writings by Nichols, 1978-2001 (Box 286, Folder 26)
      - Originals of articles by Nichols for TWN and other Florida-based publications, 1981-1998 (Box 286, Folder 27)
      - Skir, writing-related clipping; Weinberg, copies of Gay columns, 1972-1973, undated (Box 286, Folder 28)
- Oversize Material, 4 boxes
  Consists almost entirely of printed material - including clippings, magazines, newspapers, and posters - removed from series in the James Sears collection. Arranged in alphabetical order by series name.
  - Other Activities Series, 2007-2008
    - Sea Island Community, 2007-2008, 6 folders
      Newspapers and other printed materials, arranged by title.
      - Sea Island files (Box 290)
  - Professional Papers Series, 1996-2002
    - Conferences and Organizations,1996-2002
      - South Carolina Gay and Lesbian Pride (SC Pride), newspapers, 2002 (Box 290)
    - Engagements and Publicity, 1996-2001
      - Clippings and newspapers, 1996-2001, 2 folders (Box 290)
      - Clippings and newspapers, 1997-2001 (Box 293)
      - Dust jackets, flyers, and posters, 1997-2001 and undated (Box 293)
      - Oversize posters, circa 2000-2002 (Sears as main speaker in all of these events) (Oversize-folder 1)
        - Rutgers "Coming Out Day," 2002 (Oversize-folder 1)
        - Sears lecture, "Calling the Shots," circa 2000 (Oversize-folder 1)
        - "Southern Sexual Identity Film Series," location unidentified, circa 2000 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Teaching, 1993-2004
      - Clippings and newspapers, 1993-2004 (Box 293)
  - Research and Writings Series, 1934-1935, 1975-2007 and undated
    - Major Works, 1934-1935, 1997-2001
      - Lonely Hunters, printed materials, 1997-1998, 2 folders (Box 290)
        Consists of clippings, magazines, and newspapers containing reviews, announcements of readings and appearances by Sears. There are also other printed publicity items in this series.
      - Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones, printed materials, 2001, 5 folders (Box 291)
        Clippings, magazines, and newspaper issues contain reviews, announcements of readings and appearances by Sears. Also included are printed publicity materials.
      - John and Edwin, copies of The Shako literary magazine, 1934-1935 (Box 291)
        Photocopies of literary newspaper published at The Citadel, Charleston, South Carolina. (A shako is the tall military hat worn by cadets at the Citadel.)
    - Other Publications, 1995-1997
      - Centering Culture: Teaching for Critical Sexual Literacy Using the Sexual Diversity Wheel, print materials, 1995-1997 (Box 291)
    - Research Files, 1975-2007 and undated
      - Florida files: gay and lesbian community newspapers, various cities, 1976-1981 and undated (Box 293)
      - International files: posters and magazines, various countries, 2005-2007 and undated (Box 293)
      - Printed material files: gay and lesbian community newspapers, various cities, 1975-1999, 4 folders (Box 292)
      - Southern states files: gay and lesbian community newspapers, various cities, 1981-1998, 2 folders (Box 292)
      - Southern states files: gay and lesbian community newspapers, various cities, 1973-1975 and undated (Box 293)
- Accession (2012-0002), 2000s; 24 boxes, 1 oversize folder
  Files associated with academic journals edited by Sears (boxes 294-299); books written or edited by Sears (boxes: 300, 301, 309-314); the Greater Park Circle Film Society co-founded by Sears (boxes 301, 302, and oversize material); Sears' real estate career (boxes 303 and 304); other writings by Sears (box 304); subject and research files (boxes 305-308); and A/V material (boxes 315-317).
  Conditions Governing Access
  [Original media are closed to use; access may require the production of listening or viewing copies.]
  - Journal of Gay and Lesbian Issues in Education, 2006-2007 (Box 294)
    Submissions, correspondence, final article typescripts.
  - Journal of LGBT Youth, 2006-2007 (Box 294)
    Submissions, correspondence, contracts, final article typescripts. Includes 3.5" floppies.
  - Journal of Gay and Lesbian Issues in Education, 2007-2009 (Box 295)
  - Journal of LGBT Youth, 2007-2009 (Box 295)
  - Journal Issues: Journal of Gay and Lesbian Issues in Education and Journal of LGBT Youth, 2006-2011 (Box 296)
  - Journal of LGBT Youth (Box 297-299)
    Submissions, correspondence, final article typescripts. Boxes 298 and 299 have CDs and floppies.
  - Surveys and data sets for follow-up book to Growing Up Gay in the South (Box 300)
  - Research files for follow-up book to Growing Up Gay in the South (Box 301)
  - Workshop material (Box 301)
  - Greater Park Circle Film Society files (Box 301)
    See additional materials in Oversize Folder 1.
  - Greater Park Circle Film Society files (Box 302)
  - Real estate business material: ephemera, promotional material, writings, correspondence (Box 303)
  - Real estate business material: ephemera, promotional material, writings, correspondence (Box 304)
  - My Park Circle files (Box 304)
  - Writings by Sears (on topics other than real estate) (Box 304)
  - Subject and research files: Berkshire Museum-Bragg, Laura (Box 305)
  - Subject and research files: Bragg, Laura-Columbia University (Box 306)
  - Subject and research files: Foreman, Clark-Valentine Museum (Box 307)
  - Subject and research files: new A-Z series (Box 308)
  - Fan letter with DVD (Box 308)
  - University of Arizona LGBT Studies position (Box 308)
  - Turning Points in Curriculum: A Contemporary American Memoir, 1994-2000 (Box 309)
    - Interviews and transcripts (Box 309)
    - Turning Points research files and interview tapes (audiocassettes) (Box 310)
      [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
    - Typescripts (Box 311)
    - Reviews, permissions, prospectus, contracts, production schedules, payments, correspondence (Box 312-313)
    - New edition: contracts, correspondence, typescripts, etc., 2002-2007 (Box 314)
  - Audiovisual materials (Box 315-317)
    Boxes contain VHS tapes of LGBT-themed events, documentaries, TV series, TV news, and student presentations (Box 314: 9 tapes; Box 315: 10 tapes), most are labeled.
    Box 316 has 9 CDs and DVDs of photos and writings (3 of these are Jack Nichols material), all labeled; 6 audiocassettes: 5 contain material related to Sears book, Lonely Hunter, 1 unlabeled; 6 reels (audio): 5th annual Mattachine Society Convention, 1959 and 5 labeled "NACHO 1966" (NACHO=North American Conference of Homophile Organizations).
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Access may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Film posters from Greater Park Circle Film Society (Oversize-folder 2)